Chepstow Collection
The Preservation Society of Newport County
Chepstow Collection
1954 1996
1954 1986
PSNCA.H.010
Photos, financial records, and ephemera related to the house "Chepstow" during the ownership of Alletta Morris (MacDonald) McBean.
The Preservation Society of Newport County 424 Bellevue Avenue Newport, RI 02840 Tel: 401-847-1000 museumaffairs@newportmansions.org
Various Creators
3 Hollinger boxes.
Scope and Content Note
The Chepstow Collection encompasses photos, financial records, property records, and ephemera documenting the history of the house "Chepstow", located on Narragansett Avenue in Newport, Rhode Island. This collection does not include the personal papers of any Chepstow residents.
Biographical/Historical Note
Chepstow is an Italianate-style house on Narragansett Avenue in Newport, Rhode Island. Built in 1860 for Edmund Henry Schermerhorn, a descendant of Simon Jacobse Schermerhorn and cousin to Caroline Webster Schermerhorn Astor, the house was designed by notable Newport architect George Champlin Mason and built by Cyrus H. Peckham. Beginning in 1860 with the construction of the Schermerhorn and Edward Ogden houses, Mason transformed the Narragansett Avenue neighborhood into one of Newport's earliest cottage colonies, featuring Chepstow and its neighbors, Gravel Court and Starboard House. Like other Mason houses built in the Italianate style, including the now-demolished By-The-Sea, Chepstow's design includes a French or Mansard roof and a distinctive single-story bay window to one side of the front entrance. Despite a series of additions, Chepstow retains many of its original design features, including smooth exterior boarding, first-floor arched windows, and bracketed trim. The house was additionally noteworthy during its 1860 construction for utilizing Caen stone for its exterior stairs, "the only specimen of this stone on the island" at the time.
Although the house was originally constructed as a summer cottage, Edmund Schermerhorn for six or seven years... had lived the life of a recluse ("Death of a Rich Recluse", The New York Times, October 2, 1981, Times Machine) as a year-round resident. Schermerhorn never married and had no children, and upon his death in 1891, the house was willed to his brother, William Colford Schermerhorn. William Schermerhorn utilized the property only as a summer residence, but expanded the house's living space through an addition to the west side of the building. Upon his death, William Schermerhorn willed all of his real estate to his wife, Ann E.H. Cottenet Schermerhorn, who in turn willed shares of the property to their three daughters. Following the deaths of Ann Schermerhorn and her daughter, Sarah, the property was sold to R. Horace Gallatin in 1911 for an undisclosed price. Ownership was transferred to Gallatin's wife, Emily Lorillard Morris Gallatin, in 1913. Over the following years, Emily Morris Gallatin purchased an adjoining parcel of land to expand the property to its current extent, and named the estate "Chepstow" in honor of the town in Wales from which the Morris family originated. In 1949, following the death of both Emily and R. Horace Gallatin, the property was purchased for by Alletta Nathalie Lorillard Morris MacDonald (later Alletta Morris McBean), the daughter of Emily Morris Gallatin's cousin, Lewis Gouverneur Morris.
Alletta Morris (MacDonald) McBean utilized the estate as a summer residence from 1949 until her death in 1986. In the 1970s, she oversaw the addition of a "Garden Room" at the rear of the building, and applied her skill and passion for découpage to many surfaces throughout the home. Alletta was a noted hostess among Newport summer residents; her Chepstow table settings were featured in the August 1982 issue of _Town and Country_ magazine, and, along with her second husband, Peter McBean, she hosted an annual banquet dinner at Chepstow during the weekend of the Newport Country Club golf tournament. Among many other philanthropic ventures, Alletta was a Trustee of The Preservation Society of Newport County, and was posthumously awarded the Society's Antiquarian Medal in 1986. Alletta gifted Chepstow to the Preservation Society in her will, with the provisions that her husband, Peter McBean, would retain the right to use the property as his summer residence until his death, and that the house would be preserved as a historic house museum. In 1998, following the 1997 death of Peter McBean, the house opened to the public as a museum, and continues to open for tours throughout the summer.
The collection is open to the public, and there are no restrictions on access. However, the collection can only be seen by scheduled appointment.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in three series across three Hollinger boxes.
Series 1: Photographs
Series 2: Financial and Property Records
Series 3: Ephemera
Works about Chepstow
Cann, Ross, “Newport Spotlight: Chepstow Mansion,” A4 Architecture + Planning, Inc., August 25, 2022, Article.
Jordy, William H., “Edward H. Schermerhorn House (Chepstow),” Society of Architectural Historians (SAH) ARCHIPEDIA, July 17, 2018. Archipedia entry.
Materials consulted in creation of finding aid.
"Death of a Rich Recluse," The New York Times, October 2, 1891, Times Machine
The Newport Mercury, October 20, 1860, accessed via the Internet Archive.
City of Newport, R.I. Land Evidence Records, viewed in person at Newport City Hall.
Names
Mason, George Champlin, 1820-1824; Peckham, Cyrus H., b. circa 1828; Schermerhorn, Edmund Henry, 1815-1891; Schermerhorn, William Colford, 1821-1903; Gallatin, R. (Rolaz) Horace, 1871-1948; Gallatin, Emily (Morris), 1873-1944; McBean, Alletta Morris (McDonald), 1912-1986; Schermerhorn family; Morris family
Places
Newport Rhode Island 41.4833, -71.3000
Subjects
Architecture
- Series 1: Photographs, PSNCA.H.010.01 (Box 1)
  - Exterior (Architecture) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Exterior (Carriage house) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Exterior (Grounds) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Interior (Entrance Hall) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Interior (Sitting Room) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Interior (Library) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Interior (Drawing Room) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Interior (Dining Room) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Interior (Dining Room) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Interior (East Porch) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Interior (Garden Room) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Interior (Pantry) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Interior (Kitchen) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Interior (Second Fl. Hall and Sitting Rm.) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Interior (Mrs. McBean's Bedroom) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Interior (Mr. McBean's Bedroom) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Interior (South Bedroom) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Interior (North Bedroom) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Interior (West Bedroom) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Additional Photos (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Unidentified (Hand with plants) (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Unidentified (Small airplane) (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Front entrance (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Photos of Chepstow table settings (1970s), photos possibly taken by butler "Buzzy" (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - "Chepstow" Interior Views 1969-1971, 1 photo album **ADD PHYSICAL DESCRIPTION HERE** (Box 1)
- Series 2: Financial and Property Records, PSNCA.H.010.02 (Box 2, Box 3)
  - 1954 storm damage appraisal by Gustave J.S. White, Inc. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Hurricane Carol, 1954
  - Supplemental photos from 1954 storm damage appraisal by Gustave J.S. White, Inc. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Tax letter regarding financial damages from 1954 hurricane., 1956 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Garage apartment plans, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Travelers Insurance letter regarding burglary of 30 January 1974 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1986 inventory of Alletta Morris McBean estate, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Found in Chepstow 2nd Floor Sitting Room Alcove in bottom drawer of desk.
    A Mahogany Tambour Desk ( PSNC.8093 ) located in the Chepstow 2nd Floor Sitting Room Alcove, collection of The Preservation Society of Newport County.
  - Article and listings about other Newport residences, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Chepstow budget, undated, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Alletta Morris McBean inventory of Newport house, Not later than 1986.; 2 photo binders (Box 3)
    Found in institutional records and determined to predate PSNC ownership of Chepstow.
  - Additional photos from Alletta Morris McBean inventory of Newport house (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Found inside front cover of vol. 1 of Alletta Morris McBean inventory of Newport house.
- Series 3: Ephemera, PSNCA.H.010.03 (Box 2)
  - Chepstow Stationery (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Town and Country magazine, August 1982 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Additional copy of article "At Home" from Town and Country magazine, August 1982 (Box 2, Folder 11)